Welcome everybody, this is Yasser Ossaily from learn dental series.
In this episode, we will continue our discussion about diagnosis and treatment
planning in operative dentistry.
Let me declare that I don't receive fee, compensation or royalties from the
sales of any of the products shown or discussed and this presentation has not
been sponsored by any company, agency or organization and is only prepared for
educational purposes.
This presentation is copyright protected and could not be transmitted by any
mean unless you have a prayer permission from the author.
Still, we are discussing how to properly diagnose, dental caries by different
techniques and by, different detection tools.
In our first part of this topic, we discussed patient assessment and information
gathering in terms of demographic data, chief complaint, medical history, and
dental history.
Then we go forward for the clinical examination still up till now, we are trying
to finish examination and detection of dental caries, we discussed all
traditional techniques including visual examination, tactile examination,
radiographic examination, and what are the advancements in each of these
techniques to get proper detection of our caries lesion.
Then in the previous episode, we discussed in details advanced caries detection
lesion and what are the validity of of these tests and what are the reliability
of using such devices.
Today we will discuss to complete the picture of detection of dental caries, we
will discuss caries risk assessment.
As we discussed before, it is not only detection of caries lesion, but diagnosis
means that you are detecting the presence or absence of caries lesion and what
are the factors responsible for creation and development of such a lesion.
Because our role is not only treating the existing lesion, but only we should
guarantee the success, prognosis or successful prognosis of our restorative
management as well as prevention of formation of another caries lesion.
That's why we should collect data about all the environment and the
circumstances related to this caries lesion.
What are the factors that resulting in inducing this lesion, why it is a
chronic, why it is acute, why it is active, why it is inactive, and how to
manage it properly.
Okay? That's why we are discussing now caries risk assessment.
Because before we will go for the discussion of what are the caries risk
assessment and how we could perform it, let us start with the caries risk
factors.
Caries risk assessment is important part of overall the process of patient care
as we discussed.
So, you must gather all the appropriate data from examination, okay, and from
interviewing the patient, okay, for caries detection to formulate an overview of
your risk factor related to this patient and how to identify the positive
factors.
Okay? In general, according to international caries classification and
management system,
Patient level, okay, you are detecting data related to the person himself
including his attitude, including his previous experience, okay, in all the
health services.
But intraoral it is related only to your cavity and to the situation and
relations of teeth to other environmental factors intraorally.
Let us start with patient level caries risk factor.
The most risky factor or the most aggressive risk factor is radiation, a patient
recording or reporting that he received head and neck radiation.
This affects many major salivary glands and affects their secretion, affecting
the oral flora, affecting the general health of your patient.
That's why once your patient reported that he received head and neck radiation,
then he is classified automatically as a high-risk patient.
Okay? Regarding your caries, high caries risk patient.
Then coming dry mouth conditions, okay, either related to local condition
related to medication, related to, recreational, drug or self-reported, okay, by
the patient.
Okay?
Inadequate oral hygiene brackets, the patient didn't mention that he practicing
or performing any prophylactic oral hygiene measures including flossing,
including brushing, okay, infrequent brushing, okay,
and so on.
Okay?
Deficient to exposure to topical fluoride, your patient is not exposed to
topical fluoride and at the same time he already consumed high frequency amount
of sugary drinks and snack.
Okay?
And when you ask him about his chief complaint and his past dental history,
okay, he will mention that he is coming to your dental clinic whenever he having
a great problem that he could not solve by himself.
Then this is called symptomatic driven dental attendance.
Okay? If you remember when we asked about the dental history, okay, in the first
episode, we said that one of its important, it describes the degree of interest
of your patient, okay,
and the culture medical culture and dental culture you have, the dental
knowledge you have about the importance of early diagnosis.
Okay? Socioeconomic status also plays a major role as low economic status acting
as a health access barrier.
Okay, that's why your patient may postpone the treatment maybe become
asymptomatic driven dental attendance because of his socio-economic status.
For for children, high caries experience of mother or cave givers, okay?
Will reflect the attitude of the family, will reflect the degree of interest of
mother or caregiver to preserve his teeth.
Okay? Then coming for our clinical examination to go for intraoral level of
caries risk factors.
Number one, hyposalivation.
Is a gross indicator for dry mouth.
And the bofa index is also an indicator whenever the patient has hyposalivation,
okay, and whenever the patient bofa index is high,
okay, as we discussed before which is related to exposed pulp ulceration,
fistula, abscess or these dental sepsis related to untreated caries lesion as a
sequela of untreated caries lesion.
When both of them are high, then the patient also is automatically considered as
a high caries risk patient.
Then we have now three major factors that classify your patient without any
details or without going for much more details,
classifying your patient as a high caries risk patient.
Number one, at the patient level, patients receiving head and neck radiation.
Number two, at the intra oral level, patient reporting hyposalivation or patient
with high bofa index, okay?
Then the caries experience and active lesions, okay, also indicates either the
patient is high caries risk or low caries risk according to the number of caries
experiences and the number of active lesions you will find.
Then coming the presence of thick black evidence of sticky biofilm in black that
reflects the degree of oral hygiene of oral hygiene measurements the patient
follow.
Sometimes your patient when you ask him directly about his oral hygiene
measures, he already reported that he is brushing his teeth, okay?
But he didn't know actually he's not telling a lie, actually he's telling the
truth, but maybe he's using a wrong brush long wrong technique,
okay, just brushing his anterior teeth, he didn't use mouthwash, he didn't use
toothpicks, he didn't use dental floss, he didn't floss his teeth.
Okay? And he thought that by this technique he already preserving or having a
good oral hygiene.
Okay? But actually clinical examination reveals that the patient having a thick
black, that means that there is a much more problems in his oral hygiene that he
could imagine.
Also presence of appliances, restorations.
Okay, all of these causes increased biofilm retention, teeth crowding and
malocclusion.
Okay? That's why comes the importance of orthodontics, not only aesthetic, but
also it is a means of recreating a good relation between teeth and each other.
Okay? That's why it facilitates much more cleaning and produces less retention
and less stagnation of your cariogenic carbohydrates.
Okay? Exposed root surfaces also increases the risk of caries.
That are the caries risk factors that we are searching about and we are trying
to collect data.
How we could collect these data to determine the exact caries risk assessment to
the patient?
Number one, the American Dental Association caries risk assessment.
It is the simplest, most common one.
Okay? Where you have a sheet, this sheet is classified into sections and at the
same time is classified into three main columns where the first one, okay, the
answers when lying in the first one, then it is low risk, which is coded as
green, as you could see in this part, okay, or in this picture.
This is the picture of the caries risk assessment sheet according to American
Dental Association that we will discuss now in details.
Then comes the second one, when your answers lies in the second column which is
coded as yellow,
then it is a moderate risk, if it is comes to the red one or the pale pink one,
then it is a high risk one.
Then let us discuss the first section and this section including the patient
general data, patient name, birth date, age, date of assessment and initials.
Okay? This is a routine data, demographic data you have collected from all your
patients.
Then comes our caries risk assessment.
The first part, okay, is related to contributing conditions, which is fluoride
exposure, frequency and amount of sugary foods or drinks including juice,
carbonated beverages, noncarbonated soft drinks,
caries experience of mother or caregiver, okay, for those whose age is between 6
to 14 years old and dental home care, okay, recorded by the patient, okay, and
advised by dental office.
And you have the patient answer about this, yes or no?
Frequent or not frequent, okay, no caries lesion in the last 24 months.
And as you are going and those are the three columns in which you are
classifying the answer, which is beneath or under the low risk category or
moderate risk or high risk category.
Then comes the second part, okay, which describes the general health conditions.
Okay? Remember that all of these cases are related to patient level factors
until now, we are not introduced yet to clinical examination and to the
intraoral factors.
This group includes general health, special health care needs, okay, either
developmental, mental disabilities, okay, that affects the healthcare.
Okay, how could your patient perform his healthcare, okay, especially oral
hygiene measures?
Chemo or radiotherapy, okay, as you could notes from chemo or radiotherapy, the
answer is no or yes.
Low risk or high risk, you don't have in between, because as we mentioned
before, patient receiving head and neck radiation is automatically classified as
high risk.
Okay? Then eating disorders, has eating disorder no or yes.
Okay? It is not classified as a high risk, but it ranged between low and
moderate.
Medications that reduce salivary flow.
Okay? Drugs or alcohol abuse, okay?
This is all of these factors up till now related to the patient level risk
factors.
Then comes the final clinical conditions which are related to the intraoral
level factors.
Okay? Including cavitated or non-cavitated lesions, caries lesions or
restorations, what are the number of them within the last 36 months, okay, at
least, having no caries lesion or having one or two or having three or more.
The is missing due to caries in the past 3 years, okay, visible black.
Okay, unusual tooth morphology that motivates or that favor accumulation and
food stagnation.
Exposed root surfaces, restorations with overhangs or open margins or open
contact, dental appliances, especially orthodontics.
Severe or dry mouse zerostomia, and then comes the last part, which is the
overall assessment of the case.
Either low, moderate or high. It's very simple.
As long as all your answer in that green column, okay, then it is low.
If one answer is shifted to the right one, which is yellow one to the moderate,
then it is classified as moderate, okay?
If the patient having even just one answer in the high risk column, then he is
classified according he is classified as high risk patient.
And in this chart, you could record your instructions, what instructions you are
advising the patient according to what is missing, what is the worst condition.
Okay? If the patient recording that he is not receiving chloride and his
classified as high risk.
Then comes the second part, which describes the general health conditions, okay?
Remember that all of these cases are related to patient level factors until now.
We are not introduced yet to clinical examinations and to the intraoral factors.
This group includes general health, special healthcare needs, okay, either
developmental, mental disabilities, okay, that affects the healthcare.
Okay, how could your patient perform his healthcare, okay, especially oral
hygiene measures?
Chemo or radiotherapy, okay?
Caries risk assessment is an important part of overall the process of patient
care as we discussed.
So, you must gather all the appropriate data from examination, okay, and from
interviewing the patient, okay,
for caries detection to formulate an overview of your risk factor related to
this patient and how to identify the positive factors.
Okay? In general, according to international caries classification and
management system,
okay, caries risk factors are classified into two groups, patient level caries
risk factors and intra-oral level caries risk factors.
Patient level, okay, you are detecting data related to the person himself
including his attitude, including his previous experience, okay,
in all the health services, but intra-oral it is related only to your cavity and
to the situation and relations of teeth to other environmental factors
intra-orally.
Let us start with patient level caries risk factor, the most risky factor or the
most aggressive risk factor is radiation, a patient recording or reporting that
he received head and neck radiation.
This affects many major salivary glands and affects their secretion, affecting
the oral flora, affecting the general health of your patient.
That's why once your patient reported that he received head and neck radiation,
then he is classified automatically as a high-risk patient.
Okay? Regarding your caries, high caries risk patient.
Then coming dry mouth conditions, okay, either related to local condition
related to medication, related to recreational drug or self-reported, okay, by
the patient.
Okay?
Inadequate oral hygiene brackets, the patient didn't mention that he practicing
or performing any prophylactic oral hygiene measures including flossing,
including brushing, okay,
unfrequent brushing, okay, and so on.
Okay?
Deficient to exposure to topical fluoride, your patient is not exposed to
topical fluoride and at the same time he already consumed high frequency amount
of sugary drinks and snack.
Okay?
And when you ask him about his chief complaint and his past dental history,
okay, he will mention that he is coming to your dental clinic whenever he having
a great problem that he could not solve by himself.
Then this is called symptomatic driven dental attendance.
Okay? If you remember when we asked about the dental history, okay, in the first
episode, we said that one of its important, it describes the degree of interest
of your patient,
okay, and the culture medical culture and dental culture you have, the dental
knowledge you have about the importance of early diagnosis.
Okay? Socio-economic status also plays a major role as low economic status
acting as a health access barrier.
Okay, that's why your patient may postpone the treatment, maybe become
asymptomatic driven dental attendance because of his socio-economic status.
For for children, high caries experience of mother or cave givers,
okay, will reflect the attitude of the family, will reflect the degree of
interest of mother or caregiver to preserve his teeth.
Okay?
Then coming for our clinical examination to go for intraoral level of caries
risk factors.
Number one, hyposalivation.
Is a gross indicator for dry mouse.
And the bofa index is also an indicator whenever the patient has hyposalivation,
okay, and whenever the patient bofa and this is high, okay, as we discussed
before which is related to exposed pulp ulceration, fistula, abscess
or these dental sepsis related to untreated caries lesion as a sequela of
untreated caries lesion when both of them are high, then the patient also is
automatically considered as a high caries risk patient.
Then coming dry mouse conditions, okay, either related to local condition
related to medication, related to recreational drug or self-reported,
okay, by the patient.
Okay?
Caries risk assessment is an important part of overall the process of patient
care as we discussed.
So, you must gather all the appropriate data from examination, okay, and from
interviewing the patient, okay,
for caries detection to formulate an overview of your risk factor related to
this patient and how to identify the positive factors.
Okay? In general, according to international caries classification
and management system, okay, caries risk factors are classified into two groups,
patient level caries risk factors
and intra-oral level caries risk factors. Patient level,
okay, you are detecting data related to the person himself including his
attitude, including his previous experience, okay,
in all the health services, but intra-oral it is related only to your cavity and
to the situation and relations of teeth to other environmental factors
intra-orally. Let us start with patient level
caries risk factor, the most risky factor
or the most aggressive risk factor is radiation, a patient recording
or reporting that he received head and neck radiation. This affects many major
salivary glands
and affects their secretion, affecting the oral flora, affecting the general
health of your patient.
That's why once your patient reported that he received head and neck radiation,
then he is classified automatically as a high-risk patient.
Okay? Regarding your caries, high caries risk patient.
Then coming, dry mouse conditions,
okay, either related to local condition related to medication, related to
recreational drug or self-reported,
okay, by the patient.
Okay?
Inadequate oral hygiene brackets, the patient didn't mention that he practicing
or performing any prophylactic oral hygiene measures including flossing,
including brushing, okay, infrequent brushing, okay,
and so on.
Okay?
Deficient to exposure to topical fluoride, your patient is not exposed to
topical fluoride and at the same time he already consumed high frequency amount
of sugary drinks and snack.
Okay?
And when you ask him about his chief complaint and his past dental history,
okay, he will mention that he is coming to your dental clinic whenever he having
a great problem that he could not solve by himself.
Then this is called symptomatic driven dental attendance.
Okay? If you remember when we asked about the dental history, okay, in the first
episode, we said that one of its important,
it describes the degree of interest of your patient, okay, and the culture
medical culture and dental culture you have, the dental knowledge you have about
the importance of early diagnosis.
Okay?
Socio-economic status also plays a major role as low economic status acting as a
health access barrier.
Okay, that's why your patient may postpone the treatment, maybe become
asymptomatic driven dental attendance because of his socio-economic status.
For for children, high caries experience of mother or cave givers,
okay, will reflect the attitude of the family, will reflect the degree of
interest of mother or caregiver
to preserve his teeth.
Okay?
Then coming for our clinical examination to go for intraoral level
of caries risk factors.
Number one, hyposalivation.
Is a gross indicator for dry mouse.
And the bofa index is also an indicator whenever the patient has hyposalivation,
okay, and whenever the patient bofa and this is high, okay,
as we discussed before which is related to exposed pulp ulceration, fistula,
abscess or these dental sepsis related to untreated caries lesion as a sequela
of untreated caries lesion.
When both of them are high, then the patient also
is automatically considered as a high caries risk patient, then we have now
three major factors that classify your patient without
any details or without going for much more details, classifying your patient as
a high caries risk patient.
Number one, at the patient level, patients receiving head and neck radiation.
Number two, at the intraoral level, patient reporting hyposalivation or patient
with high bofa index, okay?
Then the caries experience and active lesions, okay, also indicates either the
patient is high caries risk
or low caries risk according to the number of caries experiences and the number
of active lesions you will find. Then coming the presence of thick black
evidence of sticky biofilm in black that reflects the degree of oral hygiene of
oral hygiene measurements
the patient follow. Sometimes your patient when you ask him directly about his
oral hygiene measures,
he already reported that he is brushing his teeth, okay? But he didn't know
actually he's not telling a lie, actually he's telling the truth,
but maybe he's using a wrong brush long wrong technique, okay, just brushing his
anterior teeth,
he didn't use mouthwash, he didn't use toothpicks, he didn't use dental floss,
he didn't floss his teeth, okay? And he thought that by this technique
he already preserving or having a good oral hygiene. Okay? But actually clinical
examination reveals that
the patient having a thick black, that means that there is a much more problems
in his oral hygiene that he could imagine.
Also presence of appliances, restorations, okay, all of these causes increased
biofilm retention,
teeth crowding and malocclusion. Okay? That's why comes the importance of
orthodontics, not only aesthetic,
but also it is a mean of recreating a good relation between teeth and each
other.
Okay? That's why it facilitates much more cleaning
and produces less retention and less stagnation of your cariogenic
carbohydrates, okay? Exposed root surfaces also increases the risk of caries.
That are the caries risk factors that we are searching about
and we are trying to collect data. How we could collect these data to determine
the exact caries risk assessment to the patient?
Number one, the American Dental Association caries risk assessment.
It is the simplest, most common one.
Okay? Where you have a sheet, this sheet is classified into sections and at the
same time
is classified into three main columns where the first one, okay, the answers
when lying in the first one,
then it is low risk, which is coded as green, as you could see in this part,
okay, or in this picture.
This is the picture of the caries risk assessment sheet according to American
Dental Association that we will discuss now in details.
Then comes the second one, when your answers lies in the second column which is
coded as yellow, then it is a moderate risk,
if it is comes to the red one or the pale pink one, then it is a high risk one.
Then let us discuss the first section and this section including the patient
general data, patient name, birth date, age,
date of assessment and initials. Okay?
This is a routine data, demographic data you have collected from all your
patients.
Then comes our caries risk assessment.
The first part, okay, is related to contributing conditions, which is fluoride
exposure, frequency and amount of sugary foods or drinks including juice,
carbonated beverages, non-carbonated soft drinks, caries experience of mother or
caregiver, okay, for those whose age is between 6 to 14 years old
and dental home care, okay, recorded by the patient, okay, and advised by dental
office.
And you have the patient answer about this, yes or no?
Frequent or not frequent, okay, no caries lesion in the last 24 months.
And as you are going and those are the three columns in which you are
classifying the answer, which is beneath or under the low risk category
or moderate risk or high risk category.
Then comes the second part, okay, which describes the general health conditions.
Okay?
Remember that all of these cases are related to patient level factors until now.
We are not introduced yet to clinical examination and to the intra-oral factors.
This group includes general health, special healthcare needs, okay, either
developmental, mental disabilities, okay, that affects the healthcare.
Okay, how could your patient perform his healthcare, okay, especially oral
hygiene measures?
Chemo or radiotherapy, okay?